Guide to the Franco Cerutti Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Franco Cerutti papers
1970-1980
GEN MSS 1164
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
3.34
(9 boxes)
Cerutti, Franco, 1918-
Franco Cerutti (1918- )
Franco Cerutti was born in Genoa, Italy in 1918. He received his Ph.D. in 1942, and was a professor of Central American history and literature at the University of Guatemala and the University of Costa Rica. In 1974 he established the Instituto de Estudios Latinoamericanos de la Universidad Nacional de Heredia (Costa Rica). Cerutti authored and edited numerous books, anthologies, and articles on the history and literature of Latin America.
Arrangement
Arranged in order acquired by the library.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Frederick R. Mayer (Yale 1950), 1982.
Scope and Contents
The papers consist of fifteen typescript volumes of writings by Nicaraguan authors, poets, politicians and others, with autograph manuscript corrections, annotations, and additions by Franco Cerutti. The writings were selected, introduced, and edited by Cerutti and bound according to intended publication series: "Prosadores decimononios de Occidente," "Obras," and "Los liberales doctrinarios de Occidente." Each volume is signed by Cerutti and inscribed "San José [Costa Rica], 1980," and contains his library stamp and bookplate. A note regarding the works of Enrique Guzman in the front of the first of the Guzman volumes is dated 20 November, 1993. The volumes are otherwise undated. An additional volume includes typed transcriptions of articles, letters to the editor, and other items published in three Nicaraguan periodicals between 1854 and 1855, and contains Cerutti's signature and inscription "Managua 1970."
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Authors, Italian -- 20th Century; Authors, Nicaraguan -- 19th century; Nicaraguan literature -- 19th century; Politicians -- Nicaragua; Authors -- Italy -- 20th Century; Authors -- Nicaragua -- 19th century; Politicians -- Nicaragua -- 19th century; Cerutti, Franco, 1918-; Cerutti, Franco, 1918- -- Bookplate; Cerutti, Franco, 1918- -- Stamp
- "Prosadores decimononios de Occidente"
  - Tomo 1. Alfonso Ayón, 1980 (Box 1)
  - Tomo 2. Heliodoro Barrios, 1980 (Box 1)
  - Tomo 3. Mariano Barreto, 1980 (Box 2)
  - Tomo 4. Címon Barreto and Francisco Paniagua Prado, 1980 (Box 2)
  - Tomo 5. Juan José Carillo y Salazar and Remigio Casco, 1980 (Box 3)
- "Obras"
  - Pedro Ortiz, tomo 1, 1980 (Box 3)
  - Pedro Ortiz, tomo 2, 1980 (Box 4)
- "Los liberales doctrinarios de Occidente"
  - Felix Quiñones, 1980 (Box 4)
  - Max Jerez Castellon, 1980 (Box 5)
- "Obras"
  - Manuel Tijerino Loasiga, Poesias, and Adán Vivas G., Obras en versos, 1980 (Box 5)
  - Maximo Jerez, Escritos: Discursos y documentos varios de su actuación, 1980 (Box 6)
  - Modesto Barrios, Escritos y discursos, 1980 (Box 6)
- Eco Popular, Las Avispas, Boletin Oficial, 1970 (Box 7)
  Scope and Contents
  Typed transcriptions of articles, letters to the editor, and other items published in three Nicaraguan periodicals between 1854 and 1855.
- "Obras"
  - Enrique Guzman, Volumen IV, 1980 (Box 8)
    Includes typescript note dated 20 November 1993, signed by Franco Cerutti regarding the three volumes of Guzman's works that were published between 1986 and 1988, and these three unpublished volumes of his works.
  - Enrique Guzman, Volumen V, 1980 (Box 8)
  - Enrique Guzman, Volumen V, Parte III, 1980 (Box 9)